A Guide to the Thomas Robinson Sharp Papers, 1859-1908
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Thomas Robinson Sharp Papers 1859-1908
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1997-019
1 container; 0.5 cu. ft.
Papers--including journals, notebooks, scrapbooks and letter copy books of Thomas Robinson Sharp, Confederate military railroad superintendent and colonel and official of several railroad companies in the latter half of the nineteenth century.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Thomas Robinson Sharp Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1997.
Biographical Information
Thomas Robinson Sharp was born on February 22, 1834, in Mt. Carbon, Pennsylvania. He worked as assistant to the general superintendent of the Virginia and Tennessee Railroad (1853-1854), East Tennessee and Virginia Railroad (1854), and the Petersburg Railroad (1855-1856). He was assistant superintendent of the Alabama and Florida Railroad (1857-1859) and superintendent of the Richmond & York River Railroad (1859-1860). From June 1861 to April 1865 he was the military road superintendent of the Confederate States of America, achieving the rank of colonel. After working as a superintendent of the Savannah & Memphis Railroad (1871-1872) and the New Jersey Southern Railroad (1872), he was an assistant, then master of transportations for the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad (1872-77). He served as a receiver for the Long Island Railroad (1877-1880), president of the Danville, Mocksville & Southwestern Railroad Company (1880-?), and president of the Cincinnati, Wheeling & New York Railroad Company (1883-?), as well as general manager of the Kanawha & Ohio Railroad (1886-?). Thomas Robinson Sharp died on July 28, 1909 and was buried in Eden (Rockingham County), North Carolina.
Scope and Content
This collection contains the papers of Thomas Robinson Sharp, military road superintendent and colonel in the Confederate Army and an official of various railways during the latter half of the nineteenth century. Included within the collection is a journal in which Sharp briefly records his daily activities and whereabouts from 1859 to 1863. He makes some lengthier entries in 1862, mentioning battles and notable individuals, including "Stonewall" Jackson and Turner Ashby. The collection also contains an indexed notebook in which Sharp seemingly recorded anything which he found worthy of remembering, including such diverse subjects as statistics and procedures of various railways; instructions on personal behavior; home remedies; tools and equipment; Confederate postal rates; and many more. Interspersed among the handwritten notes are pencil sketches and clippings from published sources. Another similar volume contains Sharp's notes on railroad history and data on a number of different railway companies. Also contained in the collection is a scrapbook of newspaper clippings, devoted entirely to an 1877 train collision on the B&O line at Point of Rocks, Maryland. The collection includes two ledgers, one largely devoted to recording sales of food goods to various individuals and companies, the other a cash book. Sharp's correspondence for a few months in 1908 is contained in two letter copy books; the collection also includes a single letter to Sharp, written by F. E. Browne, regarding a water distillery. Completing the papers is a collection of ephemera added by an unidentified past owner. These items include several newspaper clippings from the 1960s and 1970s, largeley relating to Civil War topics in Warren and Frederick counties, Virginia; research notes on various topics; an article about composition, extracted from an unidentified magazine; and a sketch of Brooklyn, Bath & Coney Island Railroad locomotive 6 ("Clifford").
Arrangement
The collection is arranged document type.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Separated Material
During the course of processing, the following books were removed from the collection and cataloged for the Rare Book collection:
North Carolina Corporation Commission, Annual Report, 1899 (Raleigh, NC: Edwards & Broughton and E.M. Uzzell, 1899). HD2767 .N8 A2 Large Spec
Biddle, Owen, The Young Carpenter's Assistant; or, A System of Architecture, Adapted to the Style of Building in the United States (Philadelphia: B. Johnson, 1805). NA705 .B5 1805 Large Spec
The Biographical Directory of the Railway Officials of America (Chicago: Railway Age Pub. Co., 1887). HE2723 .B56 Large Spec
Charters, Special Acts and Contracts of the Long Island Railroad Co., Flushing, North Shore & Central Railroad Co., and the Southern Railroad Company of Long Island (Long Island City: Long Island Weekly "Star" Print, 1876). HE2791 .L56 L56 1876 Large Spec
Baldwin Locomotive Works, Illustrated Catalogue of Locomotives (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott & Co., 1881). TJ625 .B2 A4x 1881 Large Spec
Haswell, Chas. H., Mechanics' Tables, Containing Areas and Circumferences of Circles, and Sides of Equal Squares; Circumferences of Angled Hoops... (New York: Harper & Brothers, 1856). TG151 .H35 1856 Small Spec
Hillyer's American Railroad Magazine, vol. 1-2, 4-5, no. 1. HE2741 .H56 1859 Large Spec
The Official Railway List ([S.l.: s.n., 1887]). HE2721 .O44x 1887 Large Spec
Stephenson, Rowland Macdonald, Railways: an Introductory Sketch, with Suggestions, in Reference to Their Extension to British Colonies (London: J. Weale, 1850). TF200 .S8 1850 Small Spec
Time Book for the Running of the Trains... of the Baltimore & Ohio Railroad (Baltimore: Printing Office, Sun Iron Bldg., 1872). HE2791 .B3 T5 1872 Small Spec
Index Terms
Subjects:
Civil War; Railroad; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
Contents List
- Journal 1859-1863 (Box-folder 1-1)
- Notebook 1859-1871 (Box-folder 1-2)
- Railway notebook 1871 (Box-folder 1-3)
- Point of Rocks train collision scrapbook 1877 (Box-folder 1-4)
- Ledger 1882-1886 (Box-folder 1-5)
- Cash book 1889-1891 (Box-folder 1-6)
- Letter copy books 1908, [2 items] (Box-folder 1-7)
- Letter from F. E. Browne 1895 (Box-folder 1-8)
- Miscellanea 1928-1973, n.d. (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Newspaper clippings 1928-1973, n.d.
  - Research notes n.d.
  - "Composition: How to Write the English Language Correctly" n.d.
  - Pencil sketch of Brooklyn, Bath & Coney Island Locomotive 6 ("Clifford") n.d.